This is Software Engineering Radio, the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net.
SE Radio is brought to you by the IEEE
Computer Society and by IEEE Software
Magazine online at
computer.org/software.
Hello SE Radio listeners. I'm Poe Chen,
head of engineering at ClickSend. We're
a cloud communications company.
If you're considering building text
messaging into your projects, you'll
like using our SMS API tens of thousands
of engineers around the world do. Plus,
for SE Radio listeners, there's $50 of
free credit to try ClickSend.
Just visit clicksend.com/seradio.
Now, enjoy the podcast.
Welcome to Software Engineering Radio.
I'm your host, Jeff Doolittle. I'm
excited to invite Chad Michael as our
guest on the show today for a discussion
about systems engineering for software
developers. In 2000, Chad graduated with
a degree in computer engineering. He
then graduated from the University of
Nebraska-Lincoln in 2003 with a master's
in computer science. After college, he
worked for multiple software companies
before ending up at Don't Panic Labs.
Chad is a lifelong Nebraskan. He grew up
in rural Nebraska and now lives in
Lincoln. Chad and his wife have a son
and a daughter, and Chad is the
co-author of Lean Software Systems
Engineering for Developers, the book
that we'll be talking about on the show
today. Chad, welcome to the show.
Hi, how's it going?
It's going great. Glad you're here.
Thank you.
Well, let's dive right in. The book
starts out with a distinction between
software engineering and software
development. So, give us your
perspective on what distinguishes those
two concepts.
Probably one of the big things is just
the rigor around it. I think software
development, it's pretty easy. And
probably one of the great things about
software that got us into it is how easy
it is to get going. You can really
quickly fire up your favorite editor.
Probably a lot of people it's VS Code
today, and start throwing some
JavaScript together and have a webpage.
But, did you actually satisfy any of the
actual requirements? Is the system going
to actually handle scale? Is it actually
going to be able to support what the
real users wanted out of this system? Do
we actually have much confidence it's
actually going to work? There's a lot
more rigor around software development
than just kind of throwing something
together. I think back, you know, you
mentioned my education, it's kind of got
me thinking there. You know, a lot of
what we learned in college, you know,
have that computer science background,
was more around software development.
You know, really wasn't around the rigor
of software engineering. I mean, the
number of people that have heard of
SWEBOK and actually know what that means
in software, in the software industry,
probably isn't that many. It's just
because they're not really thinking
about things as building software
systems or or doing software
engineering. We sometimes use kind of an
analogy, you know,
in some fields there's like kind of like
the physics part of it, and then there's
like the engineering, like the civil
engineering that's using that physics.
You know, computer science is kind of
like that science part. But, we don't
really focus enough on that engineering
part, the software, the really the rigor
about how to use what we've learned from
computer science and actually build real
software systems that really achieve
what our customers want. It takes a lot
more to do that, and it's
takes a lot more rigor, a lot more
practice, and a lot more discipline than
we typically see in software
development. I mean, you we can all see
the how much discipline it requires.
Just try to get software developers to
task out their work in a DevOps or any
sort of tool DevOps Jira or whatever,
and you see it takes a lot of effort
just to get kind of like that rigor
around we want to build things, we want
to know are we going to be done on some
sort of schedule, when are we going to
be done? All of those things are part of
that rigor around software engineering.
Yeah, so you've used the word rigor a
few times, which I think is clearly a
critical piece of this.
And I like that distinction you made
between sort of the the science side,
and I think what you might call the
applied side. And of course, there's a
scientific rigor as well. I don't think
you mean to say that there's no rigor
there, but it's a it's a different
rigor. It's an engineering rigor. Am I
understanding that correctly?
Yeah, and this one you're kind of going
back to that metaphor, and I don't know
who this one this metaphor particularly
comes from, you know, but you know, the
scientists they're building so they can
learn something.
You know, in the engineering fields,
we're hopefully we're learning how to
build things. And we really like that
applied piece of it. And there's some
good resources out there. I mentioned
the software engineering body of
knowledge, SWEBOK. There's, you know,
the our book helps with that. There's
Deval's book on writing software, it's a
great reference there. I've always loved
Steve McConnell's Code Complete. That's
a book that I'm like always trying to
shove down people's throats, even though
it's a little old at this point. There
are a lot of good sources out there, but
it it's kind of this soft area that's
not really talked about nearly as much.
Yeah, well, in my experience, sometimes
the old ways are best. I mean, you know,
in 1972, David Parnas wrote his classic
paper with a wonderfully long title on
the criteria to be used in decomposing
systems into modules. And yet for 50
years now, I think we've still been kind
of dancing around what he discovered 50
years ago. Does your experience kind of
gel with that?
100%. I think maybe a good test if
someone's a leaning down that path of
software engineering versus software
development, just are they aware of that
paper?
Yeah, if they know who David Parnas is.
Yeah, if they know who David Parnas is,
there's a good chance they're headed
down the right path. Obviously an
engineer, he didn't come up with a
really good clean short name for it.
Maybe a little bit of a marketing
person, and we all would have got there
faster.
Maybe too much of an engineer like many
of us. I think we are pretty good at
coming up with that long, very
descriptive name. But just having that
kind of reference of how to break things
down, how to decompose things into in a
way that we can live with for a long
period of time. That's one thing as an
organization, Don't Panic Labs, we're
very focused on is we want to build
things that we feel we can live with for
a long period of time. You know, people
aren't building bridges just so they can
have the bridge for 2 weeks and then
throw it away. You know, they're
building bridges for a long time. We
want to build our software systems where
we can live with them for a long time.
None of us are probably going to build
things that are going to last as long
as, you know, some bridges that are out
there, but we want to shoot for more
than a year or two and then we want to
throw away our software. We want systems
that live for a long time. And part of
that is that engineering rigor, part of
that discipline there. And then kind of
back to your one point, I did I do think
those sciences are very rigorous. I
wasn't calling them not rigorous. I just
like there's a particular rigor into
being a software engineer. Particular
goal of really wanting to I think as an
organization and myself and I know Doug
who wrote this book with, very focused
on wanting to kind of elevate that game
for software professionals. You know, we
want to be seeing ourselves more as
engineers, software engineers as opposed
to just people who get some requirement,
throw something out on a web page and
make it look like it works. We want to
kind of move as an industry, I think,
from that to something that's, you know,
better seen as a a true engineering
discipline that can actually have
predictable outcomes.
Do you face any resistance maybe to that
idea? Because, you know, you could take
what you described a second ago and
there are methodologies and movements
that very much seem to promote just
start code slinging, throw things at the
wall, see what sticks and iterate
towards your solution. And so, I'm
curious if you face any resistance to
the idea that we need, you know,
rigorous engineering principles in the
software industry.
100%.
We
We see resistance. Now, I will call out
internally, I think everybody's pretty
on board, you know, within internal with
Don't Panic Labs. But when we work with
others or other organizations, we can
get some resistance.
Part of it comes from this word Agile.
You know, people will throw they "Well,
that's not Agile." at you. We get that
occasionally when we're working with
other organizations. Usually kind of
have to kind of back them all the way up
and explain, you know, we want long-term
or we want agility in our project, not
necessarily to be something that's agile
or some sort of quote agile. We want
agility. And part of that agility is
actually having a plan. And we're not
going to be able to have a plan if we
don't take some time and think things
through. So, I do think there's a
resistance there. There's also a
resistance
in that people really want to just get
going. I think there's always kind of
this the very first thing people want to
do is have some idea, get people get
fingers going on keyboards. And that's
also kind of a trap. Cuz once you start
down the a path, it becomes you get a
lot of inertia one way. It can be really
hard to move that inertia to another
direction. That's why we really
encourage people before writing
software, do your designs on a
whiteboard, kind of
store things out on a whiteboard. Maybe
do some work in a Word document or my
personal favorite's more of a text file.
I prefer more text files myself, but I
don't really care how someone does it.
Just don't go straight to code. Try to
document out what are the steps you're
going to take to do things. What are the
potential things you think you may run
into? Is there any like spikes or a
little bit of research you need to do to
prove you can do this? All those things,
get all those things documented.
Document how these pieces are going to
interact within the system as a whole.
All of those things can be critical to
kind of knowing how are we going to
actually deliver the software. But back
to kind of the original question, do we
get resistance? Yes. And it all comes
back to that
people really want uh everybody get
going. I think sometimes it's from a
business side, you know, like they
really want to get something stood up
for a conference or something. I've run
into some resistance. Sometimes people
like, "Can we just not do testing this
time?"
You know, those sorts of things. Those
do come up.
Luckily, I will call out we work with a
lot of I think really good customers in
the LinkedIn ecosystem. I mean, maybe we
coach them a little bit, but I think in
general, most of our customers or come
on board pretty quickly with this idea.
So, I don't think we get a as much
resistance as some probably do, but I
will say we do get resistance. But, the
resistance isn't as bad as you would
think. People love the idea of
predictable outcomes.
You know, so if you can ever show them
predictable outcomes, I think that wins
a lot with people as well.
Yeah, and if that speaks a lot I think
as well to the fact that at the end of
the day most of the software that we're
building is supposed to be for some
business purpose, and that's the
language of the business is schedule and
cost and risk. And if you can't speak
the language of schedule cost and risk,
then you really are going to have
trouble communicating with the business
and actually solving their problems in
an efficient and effective way.
Actually, you mentioned that one you
kind of schedule and cost. It was kind
of a movement there for a while. I don't
honestly know if it's kind of a big
thing right now, but it's kind of like
this notion of no estimates. You know,
they weren't even going to try to
estimate things. And I'm a huge fan of
estimates. Well, I don't necessarily
love doing them by the way.
Right. Right.
I'm not going to claim that I love doing
estimates.
But, I do think that forcing you to do
estimates to me is kind of like a really
good check on kind of my how much I have
really thought through these individual
pieces. It really forces me to look at
it maybe with a a more critical eye or
just look at it slightly differently.
Like, how would I build this in how much
time?
Those sorts of activities, I think are a
critical part of building software. And
I really again, it really helps to
create more confidence, more success.
You mentioned the you have to talk in
that kind of language. Almost everyone
has to make trade-offs. There's very few
companies out there that effectively
have unlimited budgets and almost no one
has unlimited time. They need this
product to hit some market. They maybe
don't need it exactly June 15th or you
know, a very particular date, but they
probably need it within some sort of
time frame for a variety of reasons.
So, if you can't deliver it in that time
frame, they may literally need to make
different choices as a business.
And not being able to provide them any
level of certainty is a huge risk to the
business.
And if it's going to end up costing 10x
what they thought it was,
they also need to know that as well cuz
they may make other decisions with what
to do with that money.
Yeah, and they often don't find out
until they've already spent the 10x or
they're halfway to the 10x. This reminds
me of the old adage, you know, if you if
you fail to plan, you plan to fail.
And it's similar to another one like
it's kind of related from economics.
It's markets fail, use markets.
So, I would say the same thing. Plans
fail, use plans. It doesn't mean you
don't plan, it just means the plans are
imperfect, but a good enough plan can be
better than no plan at all.
And reminds me of that famous Eisenhower
quote, you know, plans are worthless,
planning is essential.
There's a lot you gain just by the act
of planning. And I don't think anyone
ever assumes your plan is going to go
perfectly. I think that's kind of a
myth. And then I think sometimes people
think when you're doing planning, you're
assuming it's going to go perfect.
You're not, but it is going to give you
a better shot of actually having some
sort of one it's actually giving you a
target to hit. And you have done
critical thought. Um a big thing we talk
a lot about, we talk about it in the
book, we talk a lot about as an as an
organization is critical thought.
Actually thinking about what you're
going to do, just that act of planning
can be huge in thinking can we actually
achieve these goals? One thing I think
we benefit from a little bit as an
organization, we do a lot of projects
for other customer customers. So, they
are almost demanding some of that
critical thought of us, of that resource
budget and time. I think that in some
ways makes it easier for us cuz we have
to present that back to them. It's
probably a little harder if you're an
internal organization to make the
argument we have to make those decisions
and spend that time making those calls.
They should, I'm not arguing they
shouldn't, right? But I just think in
some ways it maybe makes it easier for
us cuz our customers are often demanding
that of us as well.
Yeah, you have the natural forcing
function and I think as professionals,
we should expect the same rigor
internally and treat our employer's
money like it's our own money and don't
treat it differently just because it's
somebody else's money. I think is a an
important thing. So, let's continue on
to the next section of the book where we
talk about complexity and there's three
kinds of complexity you discuss. So, you
can maybe dive into those a little bit
with us, which is objective complexity,
requirements complexity, and solution
complexity. So, let's talk about those
three and then let's dig into how
software engineering helps address those
different areas of complexity.
Yeah, I'm going to hit the I think it
was the second one you said kind of
first.
Okay.
Requirements.
Requirements complexity. Agile tools, we
talked a little bit about it, have some
really do some good things there and
really help with that kind of
requirements complexity piece.
And I think as an industry, we've
improved there quite a bit. I think we
still have a ways to go and if I look at
us as an organization, that's one area
where I want us to continue to improve.
But that really focuses on kind of
improving that requirement complexity
area. There's not been a lot in the
industry really focused on how do we
manage solution complexity? Now, there
are things out there. There's volatility
based decomposition, which I know you
and I are both a huge fan of, but
there's other people trying to do other
options there as well to kind of rein in
some of that solution complexity. Then
there's also what we call objective
complexity. Kind of this notion of how
or what are the goals for that customer
related to this.
We often try to document like what are
the big impacts our customer is trying
to have and trying to work backwards
from those impacts, what are the
measurables
that would actually show that we
achieved those impacts with this
software development work.
Allows us to not lose sight of cuz it's
pretty easy on a software project to get
down to some sort of requirements list
and thinks that is the what the goal of
the project is is to build those
requirements.
And that is to a degree. I mean, if
you're looking at it from our
perspective, if If deliver those, we've
technically done what we said we were
going to do with that customer, but
that's maybe not why they came to us.
It was that objective complexity. What
were they really trying to achieve?
It's good to have that cuz every once in
a while you may want to jump back in and
look, are we actually trending in that
direction or have we for some reason
have we lost our sight?
Yeah, I think that's good too because,
you know, requirements very often are
duplicated or inconsistent or even
contradictory and very often they're
also solutions masquerading as
requirements. And so going back to ask
the fundamental question, what
objectively are we actually trying to
solve can help provide some constraints
on your requirements because
requirements run amok, you might end up
building the wrong thing.
And I loved your other example that's in
there that I think every software
developer or engineer has ran into is
two requirements that mean the exact
opposite.
You can't do both. I love those moments
when you get to something you we can't
do both of these, can we? That's always
a great moment in requirements.
Yeah, and you usually learn something
again about the nature of the business,
which I think that's again where
software engineering sits between
software development and the business is
are we actually understanding the nature
of what we're trying to accomplish here
or are we just code slinging and
crossing our fingers and hoping that,
you know, before the heat death of the
universe we arrive at a viable solution.
Sometimes I wonder though, you know, on
that, you know, are we just hoping the
heat death comes sooner?
Oh, man. Well, so taking those three
areas of complexity and you basically
say in the book that agility comes from
managing both requirements and solution
complexity. So, I think that's an
interesting summary. Talk a little bit
about what you mean there and why it's
your belief that agility comes from
managing cuz I don't think people put
the word agility and managing together
usually. So, talk about when you manage
requirements and solution complexity,
why does that lead to agility?
Actually, it is interesting. I hadn't
really thought of the fact that we could
have those kind of, you know, combined,
but
you know, if we're not managing things,
it's just things are happening, right?
And we're just kind of running around,
and we don't really have any control. If
we want to have agility, we're going to
need to have some control over how
things are going. Part of that may it
involves having control of our
requirements, at least knowing what's
going on with them. Also, having control
of our solution. If we don't, we're just
going to be down some sort of path. And
it's not of necessarily it shouldn't be
a problem for us that if we're halfway
through a project, the business comes to
us and says, "We need some other feature
really quickly into this work, right?"
That shouldn't be a problem. We want to
be agile. That does mean potentially
that means things are going to change,
and potentially we're going to have to
change what scope we do, we're going to
have to change some dates.
But ideally, if we have a good plan in
place, we can move things around to
accommodate that need that comes up
later. I think we shouldn't be afraid of
things changing on projects. It's going
to happen. Businesses are going to learn
new things. Now, hopefully, we don't go
from being an e-commerce solution to
being a CRM solution all in one project.
I mean, there's there's limits to it.
But I think we should encourage
businesses learning new things about
what they need, and being able to manage
those, and providing that agility for
them.
And a part of that, again, you know, we
hit it a couple times, we got to provide
good guidance.
You know, we got to have the rigor to
give them, "Well, if we if we bring this
requirement in, it's either going to
move our scope out, or we may have to
change some scope, or we may have to
make some sort of design change to help
facilitate that." And a design change
may,
you know, require some extra time to
handle that. But we want to be able to
have those conversations with our
customers. We don't want, and this is
kind of along that solution complexity
side, to be in a situation where someone
comes to us with a new requirement, we
think, "Oh, we have to rewrite the whole
thing." Or, "Oh, no, we don't want to go
back into this area again." We don't
want those conversations.
And we don't want one new requirement, I
mentioned changing our design, one new
requirement ideally shouldn't require
massive changes to the system.
It should be fairly encapsulated where
it only causes minor, or maybe not
minor, but changes to a few modules or
services within that system. If we can
achieve those goals, we should be able
to continue to provide that agility for
our customers for a long time. Cuz that
is, you know, what software
engineering's largely about is making
sure we can keep keep maintaining and
growing this system for a long time.
Yeah, in your experience, do people
sometimes struggle when you try to apply
real-world analogies to software
engineering, though? Like, you know, for
example, when I think about systems in
the real world, I you know, I I tend to
think about simple things that people
are familiar with, like, say a water
heater. And maybe you have a gas water
heater, but you want to replace it with
an electric cuz you know, we're
electrifying now. So, we want to replace
it with a an electrified water heater.
And I don't have to bust out the
drywall, redo all the plumbing, change
all the fixtures in the entire house. I
just go to the place where the water
heater is, and I pop it out, I pop in
the new one. And maybe there's some
fittings and some adjustments and some
adapters, but generally speaking, I can
just do that.
And I see you nodding your head, but the
listeners, of course, can't see you
nodding your head. So, it seems to me
that help me out with that. How do you
overcome that kind of resistance when
people say, "Yeah, but that's a water
heater. That's not software, Chad."
That's true. You know, water heaters
more physical, you can see it, you can
feel it. I do think that helps a little
bit people, you know, to kind of
understand things. There is some sense
of being able to feel things, touch
them, that maybe helps.
Seeing software is difficult cuz it is
largely like seeing thought almost,
which is difficult, you know, or seeing
a lot of text. That's difficult. But at
the end of the day, we want our software
to behave much the same way. You know, I
mean, we would almost want there to be
like a water heater service that has
some sort of contract, some sort of
rigid definition. And we should be able
to Oh, we need to replace this one cuz
for some reason we should be able to
write a new one and put it in there.
That is a a large goal of what we try to
do as as building our software projects
and with different levels of success and
different levels of things. You know,
like a water heater is a pretty good
example because as we bring it in, I
like your part of the example is that
it's never going to fit perfectly. Now,
you went from gas to electric. That's
going to be an easier transition cuz you
don't have the venting.
But if you did want to go from electric
to gas, I don't know why someone would
do that, but if they did, then you do
have to start thinking about well, now
we got to vent, you know, the gas out or
something. There's going to be a
potentially some other things. But
largely the function of that water
heater, the cold water coming in or the
whatever, you know, 54° water coming in
and the hot water coming out, that's
that part of the contract is the same.
But there is going to be like a little
bit of differences, you know, getting
getting the fittings aligned. That's
kind of something's going to happen and
in your case going from gas to electric
it's easier cuz you don't have to worry
about the venting. So that, you know,
those sorts of examples I do think they
are similar to what we're trying to
achieve in software, especially from an
engineering perspective. You know,
people often call or I've heard it said
numerous times engineering is the art of
good enough. You know, we're trying to
get stuff to a good enough.
We could try to create a world where you
could literally just take a water
heater, you know, it's almost like a
a plug and you're just unplugging one
and plugging a new one in, right? There
would be a world in which we could have
tried to do that. That would have been a
high bar
to everyone to achieve and
Yeah, it might be too expensive, right?
But yeah, maybe there's a case for that.
You know, there's a there's a company
that's making laptops nowadays called
the Framework Laptop and I'll put a link
in the show notes for listeners and
and they're extremely modular. So you
can pop out a USB plug and pop in
something else. It's like a media port
or a or a disk or more memory or or this
kind of a thing.
And to achieve that requires significant
amounts of design Yep. to be able to
achieve that modularity. And I think the
same thing is true in software that if
you really want modularity, you never
get there by just oopsing your way into
it. It requires design.
Yeah, 100% agree. I did not know that
there was a company doing that. That's
interesting cuz I on the laptop side,
sorry to go on a tangent here. I'm you
know, recording this on a MacBook here.
Apple's gone the exact opposite way. I
think right now there is nothing
customizable about this machine. I don't
know if that's true, but I think it's
true.
I have the same situation, right? I'm
sitting here with my MacBook Pro and
it's it's highly non-modular. Although,
I imagine that in there's modularity in
the aftermarket and then there's
modularity in the build process. And so,
I imagine there's probably a bit more
modularity in the factory than there is
in the aftermarket. And that's a design
decision and Apple's a design company.
So, they just have made some decisions
about who gets to tweak their design and
who doesn't. And we as the lowly
consumer don't get to tweak the design.
We just get to use it.
You know, that's a good point. There is
quite a bit of change at least in terms
of like different GPUs.
Well, actually now with the now with the
new ones maybe not so much from the GPU.
But, the memory that is somewhat
customizable, hard drives are still
customizable. So, yeah, there's still
there's still some. At least now they
have good keyboards. So, it's all I
don't know if I really want to swap that
anyway. So, it's got a good keyboard.
Yeah. So, and now we can take that back
to software and say if we want modular
software, how do we get there? And and
modular for who? Is it modular for the
end user? Is it modular for the
developer?
And I think the similar analogy could
apply there.
Yeah, that's a good one. And we're often
like as a news organization trying to
create situations where our software can
be changed, you know, by developers. And
we
it's important to us that it's not just
changeable from us as a software
development company. And if we're
working with someone, we are often
trying to kind of hey, this is how this
is all set up. We do try to do some kind
of training on as off-boarding if the
other company is going to take it over.
We do both models where companies take
it over and run with it for a long time
and where we keep it. And if if somebody
does, we always try to make sure they
have the knowledge so they know how it
that how we intended that design to
change.
Right. And you just said how we intended
that design to change, which reminds me
of a quote that's pretty common in the
book, which is design for change. So,
talk about that a little bit and then
we'll continue on through the book. So,
design for change, how does that relate
to what you're doing with Don't Panic
Labs and software engineering generally?
I think this is maybe might be the key
principle. This is kind of just being
it's kind of all wrapped up in that kind
of critical thought.
We want to design this our solutions
where we assume it's going to change.
Many of us at Don't Panic Labs have the
benefit we didn't get to work on great
software our entire by the way. We
worked on a lot of other things.
Sometimes it was other things we took
over from others that weren't wonderful
in previous lives. Sometimes it was
things we helped build ourselves that we
saw kind of age not the way we wanted.
And a little bit of that was it was
probably had a good design at the time
or at least seemed like a good design,
but it really couldn't handle the
changes to the business requirements
over time and the system slowly degraded
to where
every new feature became that much
harder to add to the system. And many of
us at DPL came from, you know, prior
organizations and that was something we
really didn't like about those solutions
is it didn't feel like we could just
keep adding things. It became like every
new thing added kind of a weight to
carry. So, with solutions we're
building, we've been very focused on
trying to make sure we design for
change. We want to assume it's going to
change a lot over time and almost
thinking through well, if it changes in
this way, how are we going to handle
that? And will our solution
be able to live with those. So, we're
not designing necessarily just for what
the requirements are, we're designing
for those kind of seams or those
volatilities for that system. So, we can
this area of the system is going to
change, we can make changes to this one
module or service without having to
destroy
everything.
How do you do that? Somebody, you know,
somebody's going to say YAGNI, you ain't
going to need it. Or somebody's going to
say that sounds like big upfront design.
And obviously, you know, you mentioned
before somebody could change from
e-commerce to CRM.
Yeah.
But I don't think you're saying design
for any and all change. So, there's got
to be some constraints here cuz this is
engineering and engineering is all about
constraints. So, tell us a little bit
about how do you do that? Like how do
you design for change without trying to
design for any and all change? And also,
how do you avoid, you know, speculation
of things that, you know, maybe aren't
actually likely to change?
That was a good one. I kind of like you
you're never going to need that. That
that is a kind of a good, you know, kind
of test.
From our perspective, I always like to
start with, you know, getting a good
sense of what the requirements are from
the customer.
We spend a good amount of time kind of
getting those a good sense of those. But
then we try to boil it down to what are
the core things this system's really
going to do.
You know, on the e-commerce is going to
be fairly different than the CRM. You
know, we're not going to end up with the
same core set of things.
And then we're really designing for what
that core thing the system needs to do
or the core most important features of
the system or the most important use
cases
of that of that system. What we do is we
usually go through and design that, kind
of designing each one individually, each
use case individually. And this kind of
then over kind of by the time we get all
of those designed, kind of like what
pieces we would use to build that, we
kind of roll that up and look at well,
what does our overall system design kind
of look like? And usually it's somewhat
iterative. We kind of go well, this
didn't this doesn't make sense or this
service here is being used by every
single thing in the system. That's maybe
a sign of a a problem. And kind of
trying to see how these things are kind
of interconnected. It's usually
iterative. I would say we never get the
design right, you know, the first time.
I we've never probably done that. It's
usually kind of like we look at it and
kind of iterate and keep going. I really
like myself to do that first version of
this like on a whiteboard, so it's
really fast. You can kind of like wire
kind of just do things quickly and go,
"Oh, this kind of makes sense." and kind
of change and change and change. And by
the time you get done, I often like to
kind of ask myself then a few questions
like, "This product through those
conversations, I've heard the customer
kind of hint that we might be going this
direction with this." Or these are kind
of like the future states of things. And
often kind of trying to very
intentionally picking up how that
customer kind of envisions this
changing.
Cuz they usually they have decent
insights there. And kind of think,
"Well, if that change came through, what
would I do to this?"
And then there's probably some other
ones that are kind of like common. Like
I know data access is going to
potentially change over time. And I know
some of the workflow is going to change
over time. Thinking through like, "Well,
what happens if the whole sign-up flow,
we have this sign-up flow now. What
happens if we completely you know,
change that in a later version? How bad
is that going to affect the system?" And
think about kind of poke it. I guess I'm
kind of like I see a design once we get
our design down, I like to really poke
it and kind of see how does it hold up.
The other thing I think I really benefit
as a engineer at Don't Panic Labs, is I
like to bring in someone else, you know,
like Doug or someone and let them poke
at it a little bit as well. I think it's
really nice to kind of present your
design to someone and have someone else
try to like really find the holes or
find the spots where well, you if this
change comes through, it's going to be a
a nightmare. And I also think it's good
to have engineers look at it as well or
other engineers cuz sometimes people
potentially a little closer to the code
might go, "Well, that's going to be
really difficult because of X, Y, or Z."
And I do think it's nice to get some of
those that feedback. I think you're
really looking for
you know, if we're doing design, it's
often You are looking for those kind of
reasons why not to do it this way or
reasons why not to do it that way.
And at the end of the day, the other
thing, you mentioned it earlier, we have
to do this under some sort of time
constraint. I think it's really
important.
You got to get this done, you know, in a
reasonable amount of time. We kind of
hold ourselves, we always want to get
all of this done in a week or less
of time. And if you don't, I think
you're just going to end up iterating
and never get something better. You
know, there's an old quote, "Perfect is
the enemy of good."
And I think it's really easy, any sort
of design, to start shooting for
perfect. And I know I'm 100% guilty of
this myself. If you gave me a year to
design something, it would be perfect
and unbuildable.
If you give me a week, it's way better.
So.
Yeah, yeah. The good enough by
definition is another way of putting
that quote. Yeah, absolutely. And I like
what you said about presenting to
others. I think when we talk about
engineering, you know, engineering
really is a team sport. And as you're
describing, you know, how you do this
with software, I I'm working currently
for a construction software division of
a large conglomerate, right? So, I think
construction, and I think, well, what
happens? Well, the architect creates
blueprints.
That's a design based on constraints.
And those are real-world constraints,
physical constraints, material
constraints, right? All kinds of things.
And then what do you do? You hand that
to the engineers. And the engineers are
going to tell the architect whether the
design holds water or not. And I mean
that figuratively speaking, but I don't
know, if you're building a a dam, then
they're literally going to tell you
whether it's going to hold water or not.
And what's great is that can impact the
original design. So, there's you
mentioned before is design is iterative,
and I think that's what I think a lot of
people miss when you talk about design,
they think the big W word, waterfall.
Ah, we're going to get all the
requirements and do the design that we
can never revisit it again. And what
you're saying is no, rigorous
engineering means you absolutely need to
change the design if you discover things
in these other processes that are going
to have an impact on it.
And I would say this too as we kind of
go through those reviews, almost
guaranteed something changes. You know,
it's not always going to be the same
type of things, but almost someone's
going to bring up something that's could
could be better or could be, you know,
like shooting for better is like an
actual problem. You know, someone could
find it literally won't hold water. I
mean, really we're not building a lot of
water holding software, but if there
was, you know, it could be like or
potentially maybe in our world, maybe we
won't be able to handle enough requests
with this sort of design for some
reason. You know, we know this this
single service here and how you intend
on hosting it cuz we often do like to
think through as well how we intend on
hosting it as part of our design.
Someone could be, "Hey, you're never
ever ever going to get the volume you
want out of that service."
And those sorts of things are great to
have people poking at. So, we'd prefer
to learn those up front cuz it is very
expensive to make one of those changes
potentially after it's up or potentially
even worse
after our customers or our customers'
customers are using it. You know, you
really don't want to find those things
out after users are using it going,
"Well, we can only scale up to a few
thousand users." That's just not going
to be acceptable in trying to make those
changes later. That rework can kill
software projects, you know, that
coming back and just constantly churning
on things. And the other thing I always
like to think about rework, one, it's
really bad for the business, you know,
coming back and constantly redoing
things. I actually think it has just as
much value to engineers. I don't think
engineers like redoing things either. I
think they like to do something and move
on to the next thing. Just constantly
churning on something isn't fun or isn't
good for anyone.
Yeah, and I think too, when you think
about rework in the real world, the
impact is evident. If I'm constantly
tearing out the walls and redoing them,
eventually the structural integrity of
the house starts to be suspect.
And I think the same is true in
software. It's just less visible.
And this is where, you know, things like
good abstractions can help you because
if you're at least if the abstraction is
not changing
but you know in a poor design you're
going to also be constantly changing the
interconnections between these things
and then your system is going to become
more brittle and more fragile with time
as the structural integrity of your
software becomes suspect.
Think about I we usually don't talk too
much about but yet we're coming back and
say we're making too many changes over
time. Yeah, it's like a house. You're
going to eventually have some sort of
structural problem if you're constantly
messing with it.
Yeah, and who hasn't
seen the code that's got you can tell
three different people have worked on it
and they're all variations on who's more
creative or who's more terse or who's
more you know whatever they got their
special way of doing it and you're like
you see the different perspectives on it
and without some overarching design like
you know this is how we do it we build a
house. It's always 18 inches on center.
Sorry if you're in the United States. If
you're somewhere else I don't know what
you do but you have a standard that you
follow.
And that's where engineering comes in.
You say this is just how we do it.
We're not going to recheck every single
assumption every single time. Some
things are standardized.
You're absolutely right. I think that's
critical. Sorry, you got me thinking
about this. What is the standard in
Europe for studs? Now I I'm going to
have to look that up
because we use I don't I
it's we use inches here. So what else
could it be? I never really thought it
has to be something.
Yeah. Yeah.
There's definitely have to have some of
those standards just common ways of
doing things. It's critical for us to be
you know kind of successful. You want to
hit on one of your comments you made a
few seconds ago too. Thing something I
always find kind of amusing in software
is when you're looking at a project and
you mentioned you can kind of see where
every developer you there I always view
it as like you're going through
geographical kind of like layers.
You know like you're going through the
Grand Canyon you can see all those
layers. Sometimes in software we can see
pretty much that same set of layers. You
can see this was this person for a while
then it was this person for a while.
This person for a while. And you can
kind of see how that changes over time
with projects. It's not a good thing.
I'm not calling that a good thing. It's
not like going to the Grand Canyon and
being in awe of something, but you'll
see that in software as well.
Yeah, it's kind of it's software
archaeology in a way.
It's archaeology.
And then you get blame and you realize
you used to write it that way, but now
you write it this way and you're even
making it hard on your future self,
which is also a challenge, right?
Yes.
That's always a horrible one when you
get like you do a get blame on something
and it was you. You're like, "Oh,
how did I do that?" I I think we've all
had that.
As engineers, we've all made that
mistake or had that moment where like,
"Who wrote this code?" And then you look
into it and you're like, "Oh, that was
me."
That's right. That's right. I call that
the Homer Simpson principle. Homer's got
vodka and mana is a march as it's not
such a good idea and he says, "Ah,
that's a problem for future Homer. Boy,
I don't want to be that guy."
Yes.
So, don't hate your future self.
So, you mentioned rework and on page 31
of the book, you talk a little bit about
sources of defects and rework and you
say something very interesting in there.
It says requirements and design are
implicated in a large percentage of bugs
with some studies showing them
responsible for more than 50% of all
defects. Now, that's interesting because
I have a feeling a lot of people when
they think about bugs, they're only
thinking about software bugs, but you
seem to be implying here that you can
have bugs and defects in your
requirements and in your design. Talk
about that a little bit.
That one I feel pretty confident and you
even mentioned kind of some studies and
whatnot. I feel pretty confident most of
those issues, especially the ones that
cause a large amount of rework, were
actually introduced all the way back in
the requirements.
You know, that someone didn't get some
requirement right about how something
should be stored or where something
should be stored or if we designed
something wrong. All of those sorts of
problems are where we get some the
software developer getting some ticket
that comes in 2 weeks before the product
has to ship and then spends a whole week
fixing something because of something.
That probably wasn't because of some
small code bug they put in. That was
probably some sort of requirement that
was wrong early on.
And those sorts of problems kill you.
Yeah, maybe it's the screen that the
developers assumed to needed to be built
because the requirements were unclear
and they spent 2 weeks building it and
then the business says, "We don't need
that screen."
Yeah.
Or vice versa, "Where's the screen we
said we need?" Like to your point,
that's missing and it's not there and
now you're spending But I think that's
an interesting concept that, you know,
there Gerald Weinberg talks about this
in his wonderful book called Exploring
Requirements and he talks about that the
cheapest place to find a defect is
actually in the requirements, but I
don't think a lot of people in industry
think about bugs and defects that way
and yet he shows from his studies that
it can be a thousand to ten thousand
times more expensive to find the bug in
production than it was to find it in the
requirements and I think that's what
you're saying as well here.
Yeah. One, I think if you find it in
production, the stress level of that
find is also so much higher.
You know, one thing I'm always kind of
focused on a little bit is trying to
create an environment which is really
enjoyable to work in software and I
don't think finding bugs in production
is good for anyone.
The developers don't like it and maybe
even more importantly the customers
don't like it. It's a problem for
everyone. So, the sooner we can find
those problems the better and while
we're going through requirements, I just
want to point out almost no one There's
usually very little energy to finding
issues while you're in that requirement
phase, right? The amount of energy Oh,
yeah, that is wrong. We just fix it.
There's a little baby more as we go into
design cuz if if we have a design and it
changes that design, people will be like
there's a little bit of work to going
through and fixing it, but usually not
much.
But by the time something's into code,
fixing something like that, like even on
a pull request, if someone comes in and
goes, "Well, that's not right." Yet that
whole requirement was wrong, it could be
a lot of effort. A developer could lose
easily an entire week of work having to
go back and fix something.
And by the time you're in production,
you're often in that world once you're
in production, I think you're often in
the world of having to do some sort of
hot fix to work around it and really
fixing it. You often have to play that
game of we got to get something so they
can keep doing what they need to do and
really fix it, which is very expensive
at that point. You know, you mentioned
thousand times more. Potentially, you're
fixing it multiple times. You're doing
like the the quicker version to get
something so it kind of works around the
issue and the bigger version to really
back that out to how it should have been
in the first place.
Yeah, and then if you're not testing,
the odds are that you're probably
introducing new problems while you're
trying to solve that problem. So, now
you're literally playing whack-a-mole.
Yeah. No one likes to play whack-a-mole
and that's
something that's pretty easy to get
yourself into a situation where you fix
one thing, the next build fix you
release something then you have to fix
it again. You get that comment that no
one wants to hear, "We're going to need
another hot fix."
No one wants that.
Yeah. Although, it seems like, you know,
a lot of what the word refactoring,
which you have not used, gets bandied
about a lot, but you have used rework.
So, what's your perspective on the
difference between refactoring and
rework?
I think rework is inevitable. We're
never going to get it to zero, right?
But, we do want to trend it as low as
possible.
And the reason is, I think if if we're
spending 50% of our time in rework,
projects are almost going to cost you,
you know, effectively double cuz we're
losing half our time not even working on
what we want to be working on.
Refactoring,
there's kind of this notion and there's
some books on it kind of like this
evolutionary architecture kind of
strategy. You just get stuff going and
you kind of just keep refactoring. That
kind of is the same thing as just again,
we talked earlier about not planning.
You're just going to go and just kind of
rework it into something that's usable.
My big counter there is I think what we
see in software is things don't tend
towards order. You know, they have a
natural tendency to go toward disorder
in software systems. It takes a lot of
effort just to keep them ordered. So, if
you don't start ordered, I think it's
really hard to ever refactor them back
into something that's great. So, that's
why it's maybe so important to get it in
a good kind of off on a good start.
One thing we bring up a lot is Martin
Fowler has this concept of the design
stamina hypothesis. I don't know if
you're you're familiar with that or not.
Um it's a chart basically shows, you
know, a good design line. You can kind
of get onto that good design line and
hopefully stay there.
But he kind of points out there's this
non-good design line. If you go really
quickly, you potentially can show value
faster if you're on that non-good design
line, but really quickly it's going to
kind of tip over and you're not going to
be able to continue to add features at
the rate you want. If there's one thing
that's been drawn on whiteboards at
Don't Panic Labs the most is is that
chart. Cuz we use it a lot to kind of
say, "Hey, this is We're trying to get
you on that good design line. We don't
want to be on that line where 6 months
later every new feature's really
painful."
And if we aren't doing a good job up
front getting that design, we're going
to be in that rework cycle. Where every
new thing that comes through, we're
going to feel like we need to refactor
all the time. And that's just not a good
situation to be in. We in general want
to try to avoid having to make big
refactors to systems to support one new
requirement or change.
Now, every solution has kind of variable
amounts of that. Sometimes you do have
to make something where you maybe have
to
some new feature comes through or some
big change. Maybe you do have to change
a couple services. Again, back to your
water heater example, maybe the pipes
don't quite line up. We are going to
maybe have to make a little bigger
changes at times, but we want to keep
that as small as possible. If we can.
Yeah, and you know, sometimes bad things
happen. Like when I was a kid, we had a
house that was plumbed with these faulty
connectors. And what they had done is
instead of using copper piping for the
hot water, they used PVC pipe. And then
these connectors had a tendency to fail.
And when they started failing, we
literally had water coming down from the
ceiling to the downstairs. And the
company that designed this, they had a
massive insurance claim from a damn
class action thing. So, they literally
had to not only replace all the plumbing
in the entire house, they had to redo
all the drywall, redo all the everything
like that. So, there's an example of a
bad design. And I think in software we
don't always see it. So, what I was kind
of gunning for with refactor versus
rework, my understanding of refactor
from the original people who came with
the ideas, which is guys like Martin
Fowler and Joshua Kerievsky, is
refactor is what happens when you have
tests and the abstraction doesn't
change.
That's it. So, if the tests are changed
and the abstraction is changing, you're
now doing rework. If you're improving
the algorithm without changing the tests
and the abstraction, that's refactoring.
And I think there is a time and a place
for that. The problem is we use the word
refactor when what we really mean is
we're redoing the tests and the
abstractions or there are no
abstractions and everything's coupled to
everything and that's like the
definition of rework.
No, from that perspective I like
refactoring. If all we're doing is
changing the code in one service or
something, that in general should be
okay, especially if we have tests in
place.
So, it should pass the same set of
tests.
Absolutely.
Let's talk a little bit about quality
because I think we have a lot of quality
assurance groups in software. Although,
in my experience, usually quality
assurance in software is actually
quality control, which is like we've
already built the car, now we're going
to crash test it. You're going to push
the buttons and check. But quality
assurance is different. So, talk a
little bit about the difference between
quality control and quality assurance
and then let's talk a little bit about
what you say in the book is that we
should aim for institutionalized quality
and what that means.
I'm going to step back and kind of
answer your last part of that first.
Sure.
Really, I think where we want to be is
we want quality to be kind of a
something that everybody buys into,
super essential for everybody's role,
whether it's project managers, whether
it's, you know, quality assurance
professionals, whoever is kind of doing
that, whether they're software testers,
whether they're software engineers,
whether there's people writing the
requirements, we all have to have this
quality mindset. It has to be on
everybody at all times. Quality is one
of the things where if any one piece of
that kind of chain or any one working
kind of falls below, I think it creates
a huge gap and we're going to end up
with quality product problems. So, it
has to be kind of institutionalized.
Everybody has to buy in.
And if we don't, we're going to end up
with problems. You know, the example
that Andon cord, everybody has has to
have the ability kind of pull it and all
stop, we have to fix something. Kind of
going back to those examples.
Actually, explain that a little bit more
cuz listeners may not all be familiar
with the Andon cord. So, talk about that
a little bit if you don't mind.
The Andon cord goes all the way back I
think it was Toyota back in the day kind
of with their factories. They had a cord
that if anybody is seeing problems with
the line as they're kind of running
things through their very well-oiled
machine of a factory, anybody could pull
that and they'd all stop and fix the
problem whatever it is right then and
there. Interestingly, and I always
thought this was maybe the more
interesting part of the story we all
kind of forget, is they also they saw it
as a good thing for someone pulling that
cord as well. I think immediately
anybody that hears this is like, "Whoa,
don't pull that. We don't want to." You
know, cuz we got to keep things going.
They actually considered an advantage of
someone brings up a quality problem,
we're going to all stop and fix it. I
think in software, we often kind of just
like almost assume just quality is going
to be lower than we want by default. And
kind of coming back to that
institutionalized quality, we all have
to see that we want a really, really
high bar bar for quality. Everybody
wants things that work. Nobody really
wants things that don't work and it's so
much harder to take things from a
mediocre quality to a high quality than
I think we realize as well. It seems
easy just to try to get that last little
bit. It takes a lot of effort. And we
can't just wait till the end and then
like, "Oh, quality time." and get it
there.
Well, we can try.
We we try a lot.
And your example was really good
earlier, you know, we get almost to the
end and then it's one marble in, one
marble out. I think really when you're
waiting till the end, that's kind of the
experience you get. It is you're going
to do some weird fix to fix something
and then some other thing's going to
break. You want to shoot for a high bar
right from the start. And that comes
down to having that everybody has to
have that same quality mindset.
Everybody has to be understanding how
important it is. And you can't just have
one process. There's not If there was
one thing you could do to solve this, we
would all do it
and it would be over. Cuz we all would.
But unfortunately, I think it requires
everybody to kind of have this mindset.
We have to have engineers writing good
code. We have to have designers
designing good systems. We have to have
UX designers designing good user
experiences and making sure we have all
those things in place. We have to have
like in our case like a dev lead doing a
good job with that code review. You
know, just cuz the developers are you
know, doing their best, they're still
going to miss things. Someone's got to
catch those things. We have to have
someone we use our dev leads to do this.
They have to also make sure does this
fit within the requirements of the
architecture. It's really easy just to
start breaking the architecture and have
a good design and no one's kind of
raining things in to stay in that
design. They have to own that to keep
people in that design. As we get it on
to, you know, deploy, we have to have
people testing it there. We have to have
people going through and doing a good
job with the UAT. You know, it's not
just about having software that works.
You know, it has to work well for those
end users as well. So it's it's a lot of
things to really get things kind of over
that hump. And if you really think about
how many like or big bugs can just come
of small things in software, it is a
really daunting problem and that's kind
of why I wanted to focus that we're
institutionalized quality is the only
way to get there. No one person can do
it. You just can't hire software test
engineer, problem solved. You know, it's
it's a big problem to solve and software
is not very forgiving. You know, we're
dealing with zeros. The computers don't
aren't trying to help us.
They're just objects that do things. We
have to put all the quality in
ourselves. It's a big challenge in our
industry.
Yeah, I agree in that culture of
quality. You know, what's interesting is
you mentioned Toyota and that's back
from the 1950s and if listeners aren't
familiar with Edward Deming, I would
encourage them to read some about him
because he was the one who came up with
the concept of total quality management
which ultimately became lean
manufacturing and a lot of those
concepts have been sort of adopted by a
lot of software people who are trying to
you know, do agile methodologies and
things like this and it very often
they're not an Andon cord. And what's
worse is if there's an Andon cord people
will say disparaging things like well,
that's just QA overhead. It's like well,
hold on a minute and I I like what
you're saying. It's like call it
overhead if you want, but the point is
everyone is empowered to pull the cord
and stop the line and what's funny is
Toyota's made amazing product like they
wrecked the competition in the 50s. In
fact, there's a whole story about how
the auto manufacturer, you know, CEOs
from the US went over there to figure
out what they were doing.
Right? Like they were just slaying it.
And I think that's ironic that you know,
in software we think well, if we can
pull the cord, we'll never ship. It's
like actually if you want to ship
quality and you want everybody else to
say hey, how are you doing it over
there? Maybe there's something to that
culture of quality.
And they were, yeah, outperforming
people that weren't focused on quality.
I think the non-focus or that lack of
focus on quality appears as if you're
going to get things done faster but
again, it it kind of has what it's very
short-sighted. You may create one car
faster, but you're not creating a bunch
of cars faster and potentially all of
those cars are going to have to have so
many defects. You're going to be dealing
with other issues as a company as well.
Right. Yeah, it's the whole measure
twice, cut once.
Yes.
You know, like I'll joke when I'm
woodworking. It's like I cut this board
twice and it's still too short.
Well, that's what you get. That's what
you get.
That's a tough one too. If you're
cutting it and it's too short, you're in
a really bad situation.
That's right. I'll cut it again. It's
still too short. Cut it again.
Let's talk about the role of chief
engineer. I have a feeling this is
another one of those that might raise
people's hackles. Oh, we don't want to
call somebody chief or things like that.
But look, setting aside I tell people
all the time I say software architect,
forget the title, right? There are
certain things that software architects
do. And so if you're doing those things,
then you're architecting. So in a
similar way, share with us what you mean
when you talk about a chief engineer and
how that kind of fits in with you use an
analogy of a football team. So maybe
that'll help listeners kind of
understand we're talking about with the
chief engineer.
Yeah, 100% agree with kind of your
notion of, you know, titles can be kind
of, well one they're very confused in
this industry. So it's kind of somewhat
meaningless cuz they have such wide
differences between companies. I think
you can really only have, you know, like
meaning within a company. But what we're
talking about here is having someone
really understanding and really thinking
through everything as a whole. It's
really common in software to kind of
have everybody in their own little silo.
This person's really thinking about kind
of like their requirements gathering.
This person's thinking about the project
management piece. This person's thinking
about how we're hosting it in the cloud
or something. We really need someone
thinking about this thing as an overall
process and design and system. And
someone that can everybody can go to to
kind of get those answers. This is how
we're going to do this on this right
here. And someone to me a good portion
of this that kind of ties back into your
you mentioned kind of a coach.
That person also has to be I think
somewhat teaching others how to do
things. No software team is completely
stable. There's no sporting team, like
no football team's completely stable.
New people are going to be coming in.
Even if you have the team operating
perfectly, the next season you're going
to have different people to some degree.
Injuries.
Injuries, yes. And in software, I mean
it's probably not injuries, right? They
don't happen, but it could happen.
I don't know, maybe, yeah.
Yeah, it could be injuries, but it's
probably more likely people leave or
sometimes cases like us as an
organization, we've grown quite a bit in
the last few years.
So, if someone's bringing on new people,
they're not going to be familiar with
how we want to do things. So, that chief
engineer needs to kind of help guide or
teach or educate those people as well.
You know, we need someone that can get
Hey, this is what we're seeing from you.
We need you to do things in a different
way. Education, I think, is a large part
of that role. And it's if you're like a
coach, that's often a large part of what
they're doing. They're like, Hey, this
is how you get into your football
analogies. This is how you get into your
three-point stance. No, you're too high.
You're too low. Kind of working on those
sorts of things. No, you're a receiver
at the edge. You should have started
with this foot in front and taken this
step. Or you're a DB, no, don't step
like that. You know, start with your
left leg back so you can see down the
line better or something like that. All
of those sorts of details, someone needs
to be able to know how that's being done
and kind of orchestrate that and coach
those people. And that's one of the big
things we're thinking with that chief
engineer. And again, kind of why the
coaching analogy, I think, rings fairly
true cuz there is a large portion of it
is education. Cuz no matter where you're
at now, not all your staff going to be
on the same page. And you're Even if you
do get them to where everybody's kind of
naturally seeing the same things, your
team's never going to be stable. It's
going to be changing. You're always
going to be bringing new people on.
Hopefully not continually. You know, you
don't want to just be constantly
churning, but there is going to be
changes. Hopefully it's not like Trying
to think of a There's probably a good
analogy here of some sports team that
completely got destroyed between seasons
or something. We don't want those
situations. That's tough, but new
players coming on board. You're always
drafting new players.
Yeah.
You have to get them up.
Yeah, and it's interesting because
design for change, I think, again, until
now, I was thinking of that mostly in
terms of the software. And yet,
interestingly, when we talk about chief
engineer, we're talking about how do you
design for change with the people?
And as I'm often apt to say, you know,
we've discovered the problem. The
problem is people, and the solution is
people, and that's the problem.
Which is kind of a riff on Mel Conway
who has taught us that organizations
will build systems that reflect their
own communication structures.
And so in a similar way here, it's let's
recognize things change, people come and
go. What can we do about it? How can we
have consistency of communication,
complexity containment, things like
this? And your proposal is let's have
somebody whose job is to have that
holistic view and onboard people to the
project and keep them consistently
pulling in the same direction.
Yeah, and it's really important cuz you
mentioned at the end of the day it's
always a people problem. Back to kind of
like institutionalized quality, you got
to have everybody moving in the same
direction. And you have to understand
not everybody is going to come in with a
necessarily a lot of experience, you
know, software engineering software.
Especially if they're coming from
another organization, there's a high
probability that their role was some
requirement came through the door, I put
some stuff on a web page with maybe some
sort of back end that kind of did it and
we shipped it. There's a good chance
that was their world. And you can't
expect them overnight, like in literally
you know, they started working with you
on Monday, by Tuesday they're writing
software the way you want. That's not
going to happen. And even if you have
good processes in place, good training
as they come on board,
once pressure starts hitting them,
they're going to start just defaulting
back to other behaviors. But it's going
to take someone kind of working with
them over the course of years to really
get them to where they're writing
software the way you want. It's not
going to be something you're just going
to flip a switch in someone and go.
Yeah, and you know, you mentioned
earlier in the book objective
complexity, requirements complexity, and
solution complexity. I think maybe it's
part of requirements complexity, but I
think expectations complexity is another
challenge too. You know, 20 years ago
you could just throw a web page together
with you know, the little PHP page with
a little MySQL database behind it and
just start start going. But boy, people
have supercomputers in their pocket now
and on their wrist and their
expectations are so high now that good
luck meeting their very very high
expectations by just slapping something
together and shipping it.
You mentioned that that's actually we
don't have expectation management but
that is actually be a good one to maybe
add to the list.
People over time, you know, like what
they want out of their software projects
has gone up a lot. Like what we were got
away with in 2005 wouldn't tolerate
anyone nowadays.
We have a app we're building for a
customer that just as this little side
feature has a full chat, you know, piece
to it. That's just a like a side thing
of that application. It's not
really that critical. 15 years ago that
was an app in and of itself.
Right. And now that's like an
afterthought.
Yeah, it's like, "Oh, we need to add
chat to this." Okay. You know, it's just
not the same as it would have been
15 years ago. And 15 years from now,
everybody's going to expect that chat to
be like some sort of AI communicating
with you back and forth and
telling you stories while you're doing
it. Who knows? I don't I'm just making
stuff up here.
No, but who knows, right? And I think
again, you know, we have to use
real-world analogies because we're
dealing in abstractions and with text
and code all day, but you know, I think
about what the expectations were of a
hunter-gatherer 20,000 years ago in a
cave with a fire and some furs was
sufficient and that is woefully
insufficient for us now. And I'm sorry
to those of you who are still slapping
and shipping together PHP apps with a
MySQL back-end, but essentially it's
like a nice comfortable cave and yeah,
it'll protect me from the elements and
it does solve the core use case, which
is I need to survive to live another
day,
but maybe my expectations for my
domicile are a bit higher now in the
21st century.
If you're still doing PHP and and MySQL,
maybe at least consider Laravel.
Yeah, and I don't mean to pick on I'm
just I'm thinking about like my early
days in the '90s when I was just like
literally was doing these slap and ship.
all were.
Yeah, before I discovered that software
engineering does not equal software
development necessarily.
Yeah, 100% agree. And it's One good
thing though you mentioned expectation
management and changing.
Over time, you know, things keep
changing. That's one of the things I
love about this industry is what we're
doing now won't be what we're doing
necessarily 10 years from now, but
hopefully we can build software systems
that will be we can still want to work
on that we're building now that we can
still want to work on 10 years from now.
Yeah, and as the book comes to a close,
you talk about what will it mean for
software development to be an
engineering discipline, and specifically
you talk about transformation of
individuals and teams. So, maybe as we
start to wrap up here, share a little
bit about with people who are interested
in finding out more about how do we
apply rigorous software engineering
principles in our context? What can we
do to assess the current maturity of our
team and start providing paths for
people who want to accelerate their
software engineering journey?
I think probably a good starting point
is getting some really good leaders in
your organizations that really do value
software engineering.
Again, you could use the We talked
earlier about kind of the Parnas test.
Do they know who David Parnas is? Right.
Getting some good leaders in your
organization. We're actually as an
organization kind of like actively right
now working on a assessment, a way to
assess developers from some of those
competencies all the way back to the
SWEBOK. Not really necessarily ready to
talk about it yet, or put it out there
completely, but trying to get an
assessment of where people are at and
provide training and education to get
them there. And we spend, not every
Friday, but a lot of Fridays this
summer, we're actually doing internal
workshops for our developers, kind of
taking them through some of these core
concepts and trying to kind of level
them up. I mean, one day everybody gets
some training in situ while they're
working on things, but we're very
intentionally trying to make time to
take people through kind of our workshop
series where we're going through things.
On Friday this week, we're going through
information hiding. It's part two of
information hiding we're going through
with people. And now some of them that
have been with us for a long period of
time, they're probably a little bit
like, "Yeah, I get this."
But we have to remember we have an
organization that's changed a lot over
time. So, some of them it's going to be
like, "Oh, I had no idea who David
Parnas was." You know, maybe last I
think we hit the first part of it last
Friday. There's probably some of them
that that was maybe their first
introduction
to him. So, it's
providing those stepping stones and
keeping this going. And even for the
people that have been in it quite a
while, it's sometimes nice to re-hear
things after a while. It's pretty
common, at least for the way I think
many of us learn, is you can kind of
learn something once, but when you kind
of re-hear about it 6 months later or a
year later, it maybe takes a different
meaning and more of a deeper meaning
than it at that time. At the time it was
like, "Well, I heard something." But it
wasn't until you really got it the
second time or the third time does it
really actually start to sink in.
Absolutely. I think information hiding
is a good example of that. You say those
words and immediately people think they
know what you're saying.
But if you're not doing volatility-based
decomposition, you're not doing
information hiding. And I know Parnas
doesn't call it volatility-based
decomposition, but that's essentially
what he's talking about is find the
areas of significant change, encapsulate
them in services or modules as he calls
them. And this is 50 years ago, right?
And I think that's part of the
challenge, too, is words struggle to
carry the weight of the meaning they're
trying to convey. And so, we have to
repeat ourselves and we have to keep,
you know, growing and maturing our teams
as they are constantly evolving and
changing.
And probably the last piece there, and
this is one that I know we care a lot
about, is we've tried to help a lot of
in our community like the Lincoln
Nebraska ecosystem trying to help grow
others within that area as well. Cuz
we're not necessarily trying to make,
you know, ourselves wonderful but not
helping others. We want everyone to kind
of benefit. And we can learn a lot from
others kind of along that same lines.
Just cuz we're doing something really
well here, we're going to learn from by
interacting with others. Oh, they're
doing this and it is really working out
really well for them.
So, it's we got to all work together to
try to continue to get to kind of kind
of for all of us to improve. Cuz none of
us have it all figured out. You know,
we're all on a journey of trying to get
better. And you know, at times you'll
feel like, oh, I got this really well
figured out, but sometimes just hearing
someone else's different take on it can
be pretty informative. Like, oh, this
person's trying something different and
it might have some better results for us
cuz
software development's it's hard. I
think it was a Donald Knuth quote,
"Software is hard." And it is a
difficult discipline to be part of in
software engineering. It's a lot of
effort. But if we all work together, be
part of the ecosystem, you know, this
podcast, things like this also have a
lot of value cuz it helps to kind of
spread the word about, you know,
software engineering itself, not just
software development. And try to get
people thinking more about how to write,
you know, software we can live with, how
we can encapsulate volatilities
as opposed to just what new features are
available in what new framework that's
you get a lot of that kind of content
out there. Not that that content's bad.
There's some great content along those
lines, but I think there's something
about software engineering has a even
bigger impact on the world. And there's
just not as much of that content out
there, either. There's way more focused
on what's available in this new
framework right now.
Yeah, I agree. I tend to say that people
focus on tools and technologies, which
there's nothing wrong with being a great
technician, but that's not systems
design and that's not software
engineering, right? Being really good at
using a circular saw that's like really
awesome and cool doesn't mean you know
how to design skyscrapers and that's not
insulting the guy that is, you know, a
whiz with the circular saw. It's just a
different discipline.
And I think a similar thing is true here
and people don't rise to the occasion,
they fall back on their training. So,
when your training is tools and
technology, you're going to always try
to jump to coding or jump to spinning up
a Kubernetes cluster or jump to spinning
up a Kafka, you know, whatever, right?
And it again, those aren't bad things,
but what purpose are they serving
broadly? And that's where I am really
excited that we've had you here on the
show because you don't fall back on
software engineering when you haven't
learned how to be a software engineer.
So, if you want your training to be what
you fall back on,
then I think books like yours are a
great introduction for people. And
there's a whole lot more in the book,
too, that we didn't have, you know,
nearly enough time to cover in our brief
time. But hopefully this gives people a
sense of you and what you are about,
Chad, and and Don't Panic Labs, and
people can grab the book and start
diving a little bit more into what it
means to do software engineering.
Thank you so much for this time. It's
been a lot of fun. Good to meet you, and
always enjoy talking software
engineering with people. Yeah, a lot of
people want to focus more on the tools
and technology. You're going to find a
lot of people that want to talk about
that, but I really enjoy these talks
about I'm software engineering, and
thanks for this opportunity.
Yeah, glad you're here. And if listeners
want to find out more about what you're
up to, it's Chad Michael, m i c h e l on
Twitter. And then also they can find
Don't Panic Labs at don'tpaniclabs.com,
which is the company that Chad and his
co-founder Doug are operators or owners
or whatever your titles are. Grand
Poobah, I don't know.
There's There's six of us that own kind
of Don't Panic Labs.
Okay.
There's four others, but yeah, Doug and
I kind of wrote this, you know, book.
Cool.
Awesome. Awesome. Well, hey Chad, thank
you so much for joining me today.
Thank you so much, Jeff.
All right, this is Jeff Doolittle for
Software Engineering Radio. Thanks so
much for listening.
Thanks for listening to SE Radio, an
educational program brought to you by
IEEE Software Magazine. For more about
the podcast, including other episodes,
visit our website at se-radio.net.
To provide feedback, you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on LinkedIn, Facebook, Twitter, or
through our Slack channel at
se-radio.slack.com.
You can also email us at
team@se-radio.net.
This and all other episodes of SE Radio
is licensed under Creative Commons
License 2.5.
Thanks for listening.